A Guide to the Additional Papers of Thomas Lafayette Rosser
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Thomas Lafayette Rosser
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1171-d, -e, -f
This collection consists of ca. 138 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These additions to the Rosser papers were a gift to the Library from Miss Barbara Rosser of Charlottesville, Virginia, on September 25 and October 9, 1980, and on January 26, 1981.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 138 items (2 Hollinger boxes) of correspondence, photographs, stereoscopic views, bound volumes, and printed materials relating to Thomas L. Rosser (1836-1910), the assistant chief of construction for the Northern Pacific Railroad and a former Confederate general. Most of the correspondence is comprised of letters from Rosser to his sons, Thomas, Jr., and William, while both were attending school in Virginia. Also included is a letter from General Joseph E. Johnston to Robert E. Lee, 1862, concerning the evacuation of Norfolk, Virginia.
Of great interest are two of Rosser's diaries for the years 1872 and 1873 in which he recorded his activities in the Dakota Territory and on business trips to Chicago, New York, and Washington. Several entries concern his invention of a combination canal-railroad canal lock. In the diary for 1873, General Philip Sheridan is briefly mentioned as is George Armstrong Custer, who had the assignment of protecting expeditions venturing into Indian territories. In this same diary Rosser recounts his difficulties resulting from the Panic of 1873, which was caused by unrestrainted speculation in railroad construction and wil investment schemes, and was touched off by the failure of Jay Cooke and Company, financier of the Northern Pacific. Rosser had to sell the company's equipment at auction and find other work during this period while taking care of his family. He eventually found employment as chief engineer for the Canadian Pacific Railroad, a post he held until his retirement in 1885.
Rosser's letterbook, 1871-1872, complements the diaries and contains receipts, business correspondence, a payroll, salary vouchers, memoranda on unfinished work in each section, and notes on his survey of the Dakota Territory. Ira Spaulding, Samuel B. Holabird, and Winfield S. Hitchcock are correspondents.
Fifty-two stereoscopic views and seven photographs show scenes of Minnesota and Ontario at the time Rosser lived and traveled there while employed by the Northern Pacific and, subsequently, the Canadian Pacific railroads. Some views of other places around the world are included. Other photographs in this collection chiefly pertain to the Rosser and related families.
Contents List
- Correspondence of the Rosser Family 1858, 1864, 1869-1889, 1899, 1909, n.d., 38 items (Box 1)
- General Joseph E. Johnston to General Robert E. Lee 1862 May 11, 1 item (Box 1)
- Photographs 1883 & 1890, n.d., 24 items (Box 1)
- Stereoscopic slides of the Holy Land, the Columbian Exposition, Minnesota, London, a Civil War scene, and other views 1891-1897, n.d., 42 items (Box 1)
- Photographs of scenes of Port Arthur, Canada n.d., 7 items (Box 1)
- Printed material and school reports of Gordon family members 1883-1884, 1889, ante 1910, n.d., 10 items (Box 1)
- Diary of Thomas L. Rosser chiefly re his work for the Northern Pacific Railway 1872, 1 item (Box 2)
- Diary of Thomas L. Rosser chiefly re his work for the Northern Pacific Railway 1873, 1 item (Box 2)
- Commonplace Book of Thomas L. Rosser (also contains accounts and inventories) 1868, 1 item (Box 2)
- Souvenir Booklet: Reunion and Dinner of the Northern Pioneers of 1873 and Earlier1906 Jan 10, 1 item (Box 1)
- Items pulled from volumes 1 and 5 1906, 1918, n.d., 10 items (Box 2)
- Photograph of a group of men at the Chi Phi House, Charlottesville, Virginia n.d.
- Photograph of Rugby Hall, home of the Rosser family n.d.